Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair;
But I cannot sever the tangled threads on my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
You once told me that you had only despair left for true love.
You said you were going to
forget everyone connected to the palace.
But what now of Noble Prince Guo?
What do you have to say?
You’re right.
I once said such things.
Don’t your past words count?
Things always change in ways we cannot foresee.
The past doesn't last forever.
Just like my family was in its prime,
and I was the Zhen Huan unacquainted with worldly affairs.
But that is all in the past.
No matter how much I wish time hadn't passed,
it did after all.
I don’t want to hear you say this.
Just tell me,
what is there between you and Noble Prince Guo?
I love him.
He loves me, too.
That’s it.
Good.
You haven’t told me the truth until now.
But why him?
You want to know why?
Because in my despair of love and of my life,
it was Yunli who gave me a thread of hope,
and a reason to live on.
But if you are with him,
I’m afraid your future will hold more suffering.
When I suffer,
he does too.
Since I've decided to be with him,
I’m fully aware of what will come in the future.
The hardship and grievances that you’re worried about me suffering,
I accept with wholehearted willingness.
Wholehearted…
You said wholehearted ...
But,
I’m also wholeheartedly devoted to you.
That’s different.
My heart is etched with gratitude for you.
But the love between he and I is mutual.
Even if it is a mistake to choose Yunli,
I’d rather make this mistake and never feel regret.
If you're honest,
which do you think is more important,
to be with me, or my true happiness?
Honestly,
I have always wanted to be with you.
However, even in my dreams
I know you have no affection for me at all.
If you were with me,
you wouldn’t be truly happy.
So then,
your true happiness is more important.
Thank you, Shishu.
Thank you for treating me so well.
He has your wholehearted devotion.
You don't know how much I envy him.
You too will meet a lady
who loves you with her whole heart.
Evidently, Dr. Wen cares for you deeply.
My Lady, Dr. Wen is here.
Send him in.
I congratulate Your Highness Concubine Vertu.
Good to see you.
You know I care nothing about titles.
Please rise.
Thank you, My Lady.
What’s wrong?
You look so much thinner.
Nothing serious.
What happened?
Is something wrong with Huan’er?
She is fine.
It's just that she doesn’t need me anymore.
Huan’er knows what she needs.
But do you know what you need?
It's because I know what I need
that I know I can never have it.
If you can't have it,
there’s no need to grieve.
It’s easy to say
but hard to do.
You’re a man!
Why would you let yourself wallow?
If you are devoted to her,
why does it matter if she loves you back?
You only need to stay faithful to your own heart.
If you no longer feel affection for her,
then gladly let it go.
What's the point of languishing
and making a fool of yourself?
I’ve never imagined that the courtly Concubine Vertu
could be so... ferocious.
I’m not ferocious.
In saying such things to persuade someone else,
I am also trying to convince myself.
Looking at the water,
I think back to our encounter on the lake in the Summer Palace.
I never imagined there would be a day like this.
Neither did I.
You were so bold
that you dared to visit your friend in confinement.
I wonder how Meizhuang is doing.
She’s doing well and has just been promoted to Concubine.
Except for visiting Longyue,
she still doesn’t like seeing anyone.
That is her nature:
she’d rather age in the palace alone
than beg for His Majesty’s pity.
But she’s still so young and beautiful,
yet she has to spend her life in depression.
What a pity.
You really think it's a pity?
She is protected by the Empress Dowager.
And by avoiding His Majesty's favor,
no one will have a reason to harm her.
It's the same for my Longyue.
She doesn’t draw attention as a prince does.
I only hope that Longyue can live in peace.
His Majesty and the Empress Dowager see her as "a pearl in their palm".
And Longyue herself is an endearing child.
You need not worry.
Everyone is doing well.
What you need to do now
is take care of yourself.
Yes.
I must take care of myself
for you
and for all those I care about.
Such an old thing.
You still always keep it with you.
Even though it's old，
if I didn’t have it all these years,
I wouldn't have been at peace with myself.
Sometimes, I thought that
the only thing I could keep in my life
would be this little portrait of you.
Back in the palace, I already saw you as my confidant.
But I was afraid of my heart.
Are you still afraid now?
With you…
I'm not afraid of anything.
Your Majesty, Attendant Services is here.
Your Majesty, it's time to select a concubine.
The Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Your Majesty, other than burying your head in memorandums these days,
you've only been visiting Concubine An.
Would Your Majesty like to change to another concubine today?
You are getting even bolder.
I do not dare.
I said that thoughtlessly.
Or would Your Majesty like to visit the Empress Dowager?
You have been busy with state affairs these days
and haven’t paid respects to Her Majesty for a long...
I will go tomorrow.
Arrange the sedan to go to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Yes.
The Empress Dowager is seriously ill,
yet Your Majesty often stays with me.
I am almost insulted to death by others.
How are they insulting you? Tell me.
"A bewitching minx to her master."
"Disastrous like a flood to the country."
To my ear,
these are compliments.
Your Majesty doesn't care for me.
How do I not?
If Your Majesty cares about me,
just tell me the truth.
About what?
For these days that Her Majesty has been sick,
why hasn't Your Majesty visited Her Majesty?
Is it really because of me?
If so, I ought to die a thousand deaths.
She knows better than anyone else
what caused her illnesses.
Don't get angry, Your Majesty.
You have shut yourself in the Hall of
Mental
Cultivation reviewing memorandums.
You look so pale.
Please take care of your health.
I'm aware of my health.
This morning,
when Longyue came to pay her respects to me,
I thought I heard that today was a day of significance?
Today is April 17th.
It's not a big day.
It's truly not a big day.
I vaguely remember today is someone's birthday.
Your Majesty,
let me get you ready to rest.
Here, Yue’er.
Take a bite.
Good girl.
Meizhuang, what's going on?
You asked me to bring Longyue here
and didn't say why.
Estime,
today is Huan’er’s birthday.
Concubine Vertu, you can't talk about this.
I know His Majesty has decreed
to forbid any mentions of Huan’er
and of Longyue’s birth mother.
But Huan’er…
She is Longyue’s mother after all.
I had to ask you to bring Longyue here
to show my thoughts for her.
I know you have Concubine Sourire in your heart.
I do too.
I've been aware that
His Majesty pretends to have let go of her.
But he still has her on his mind.
You see, since Concubine Sourire left the palace,
other than visiting Concubine An and Concubine Délice,
His Majesty barely sets half his foot into the harem.
It doesn't matter if His Majesty visits the harem.
My thoughts are only with Huan'er.
I wonder how she is doing outside the palace.
Since the Empress Dowager fell ill last winter,
even Madam Orchid can't spare time to leave the palace.
I'm sure she's all right!
Concubine Sourire is blessed.
No one will bully her any more.
Don't worry.
Your Majesty!
Your Majesty! Are you all right?
Mr. Su! Mr. Su!
You sleepy rabbit! Something's wrong!
Is Your Majesty all right?
Your Majesty!
What happened?
Mr. Su! Quickly!
It's a high fever!
Summon the imperial doctors immediately!
Your Majesty!
Hurry, Mr. Su!
Yes, the imperial doctors...
Summon the imperial doctors immediately! Hurry!
Coua...
Dispose of the incense in this right away!
No one can see the contents.
Remember,
keep your lips sealed!
If anyone finds out what's in the censer,
Neither you nor I will have a burial ground for our dead bodies.
Go!
Yes.
Has the Emperor been transferred to the Hall of Mental Cultivation?
We've already arranged concubines and State
Princes to take turns attending to His Majesty.
There's no need for too many concubines,
especially not the bewitching ones.
The Empress, Consort Astuce, Consort Estime,
and Concubine Vertu should suffice.
Yes.
What did the imperial doctors have to say?
That His Majesty's pulse is feeble and
floating,
suggesting that he has strained himself.
What has the emperor been doing lately?
Either meeting with officials or reviewing memoranda.
But these past few days,
His Majesty has seemed unhappy for some reason.
Who has been serving the emperor at night?
Mostly Her Highness Concubine An,
and sometimes Concubine Délice.
But neither of them for many nights.
If Your Majesty doesn't believe me,
you can check the records with Attendance Services.
The emperor fell ill at the Palace of Prolonging Happiness,
so Concubine An must be responsible somehow.
But why would the emperor be unhappy recently?
And especially for these past few days...
What was the date yesterday?
Your Majesty, yesterday was April 17.
What's wrong with this date?
Yesterday was the birthday of the banished Concubine Sourire.
If that's the case, then it's not because of Concubine An.
I thought that he had moved on.
Now I see...
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Go assure Concubine An not to worry,
and accompany me to check on the emperor.
Your Majesty, please stay and rest.
You haven't fully recovered yet.
If His Majesty woke up and found out,
we servants would surely be blamed
for not properly attending to Your Majesty.
Don't be foolish.
Am I more important than the emperor?
Bamboo, help me get out of bed.
Yes.
My Lady.
Ajin!
Ajin's here.
News came from the palace that His Majesty is ill.
His Lordship was ordered back to the palace
to attend to His Majesty immediately.
It seems to be more severe than a normal illness.
Did they say what kind of illness it was?
I don't know for certain,
but apparently His Majesty's servant
Xiao-Xiazi said that
His Majesty developed a high fever while staying with Concubine An.
But the cause of illness ...
Nobody in the palace dares speak of it.
His Majesty is often in deep thought.
Overexertion was inevitable.
Will His Lordship stay at the Hall of Converging Light again?
Yes. The Empress Dowager also summoned
State Prince Heng and Venerable Prince Shen.
It seems that His Majesty's illness is quite severe.
So, he cannot leave the palace for a few days, can he?
His Lordship cannot leave the palace, but I can.
His Lordship knew that he wouldn't be able to see you,
so he instructed me to bring you his personal stationery
hoping to communicate with you through poetry.
I will come here every day
to carry your poem to His Lordship, and his to you.
“The Loom Stretched Once.”
"Donning a spring cloak, traversing fields to collect mulberry leaves"
"Warm sunshine and fresh breezes fatigue her.”
“Yet, among the peach blossoms, the songs of trilling orioles"
"keeps her from returning home."
He can't leave because he must attend to His Majesty,
but he instead said that singing birds made him stay.
Such elegance and mischief - only in him.
“The Loom Stretched Twice.”
"Holding his horse still, the departing traveler hesitates."
“Her deeply hidden affection will remain unspoken.”
“Turning her head, she smiles, quickly disappearing into the flowers.”
“Afraid that even the blossoms might know her heart.”
Deliver this to His Lordship,
and tell him there's no need to send one back every day.
It might draw attention,
plus he must be tired from attending His Majesty.
Mistress, you truly care for His Lordship.
I'll make sure to keep it safe.
His Lordship can't leave the palace these days,
so I'm sure he will treasure this letter.
Seeing your handwriting is like seeing you in person;
His Lordship will view it day and night,
unable to put it down.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Grace to Your Majesty.
All rise.
Has the emperor shown signs of regaining consciousness?
Not yet.
The imperial doctors said that
His Majesty is weak, and
with the high fever it will take some time to regain consciousness.
These days,
the emperor
has been wallowing in his emotions.
I understand the bitterness in his heart,
and that he doesn't easily lose his composure,
but the emperor
has overly neglected his own well-being.
Your Majesty must take care as well
not to allow any harm to come to your health.
Attend to the emperor carefully.
Send someone to report to me every four hours.
Let the emperor rest in bed peacefully and undisturbed.
Yes.
State affairs have been taken care of in the meantime.
Your Majesty need not worry.
I will take my leave now.
Spend some more time with the emperor, would you?
Yes.
Huan Huan...
What was that?
His Majesty was calling the late Empress Première.
After all these years,
is she really the only one the emperor hasn't let go of?
His Majesty has deep and lasting affection.
That is not something an emperor should possess!
On this matter, the emperor should learn from you.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady.
“The Loom Stretched Four Times.”
“The rhythmic click and clack of the loom, her brows furrowed.”
“The passing shuttle weaves a drooping lotus.”
“To weave threads into a flower is easy, but
a disturbed heart is difficult to manage."
“The emotions tangled like silk threads.”
“The Loom Stretched Five Times.”
“Her carefully embroidered stitches slowly reveal a poem.”
"None can comprehend the line in the middle."
"It speaks not of sorrow, nor of languish."
“But only of the longing between two hearts."
Your Majesty, have some ginseng tea.
I don't want it.
Your Majesty is worried about His Majesty.
But Your Majesty must also take care of yourself.
Seeing how His Majesty hasn't awoken
day after day, how can I put my mind at peace?
At least Your Majesty can visit His Majesty.
Concubine An and I can't even catch a glimpse despite our efforts.
We can't do anything but worry.
We are useless, unable to serve His Majesty at his side.
We can only worry about Your Majesty's health.
Your Majesty not only manages the palace affairs,
but also serves His Majesty in the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
We still don't know when His Majesty will wake.
Your Majesty has been so worried that you don't look very well.
If Your Majesty doesn't take good care of your health,
we concubines will have no pillar to rely on.
Your Majesty, please have a sip.
After all, His Majesty became sick
in the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Concubine An, you must be held accountable somehow.
Fortunately, the Empress Dowager doesn't blame you.
Otherwise, it would become hard for us to see you again.
It's all my fault,
for not knowing how to serve His Majesty properly.
It's all right.
The Empress Dowager said you were not involved.
Don't trouble yourself over it.
If you didn't know how to serve His Majesty properly,
why would His Majesty like visiting your palace?
His Majesty has rarely visited the harem in the past couple of years.
Take Consort Astuce for instance.
She has never seen His Majesty alone.
You should cherish your fortune while you have it.
I thank Your Majesty.
Rise.
Yes.
Concubine Délice.
The Empress Dowager forbids you from attending to His Majesty.
You may go to Baohua Hall and pray for His Majesty.
As a token of your concern.
Yes.
Her Majesty is from an illustrious lineage.
Naturally she would favor women of similar upbringing.
It's already to your great fortune
that a person of your birth
could sweep and clean in her palace.
You should constantly feel grateful for what you have today.
You know you shouldn't compete with me
for favor, don't you?
Yes.
Raise the sedan.
Your Majesty hasn't rested at all.
How about getting some rest before
continuing to attend to His Majesty?
There is no need.
I haven't been able to accompany
His Majesty for such a long time.
Nor have I been able to look so closely at His Majesty.
Your Majesty! Your Majesty!
Your Majesty is awake!
- Bring some water for His Majesty.
- Yes.
"Height does not make a mountain;
the presence of an immortal gives it prominence."
"Depth does not make a lake;
the existence of a dragon gives it spirit."
"This is my crude hut–"
"This is my crude hut,
- "but my virtue is its nobility."
- Hongshi.
Mother!
Hongshi.
Mother... Why did you come here?
His Majesty's fever has come down, but he is still asleep.
How ... How come you are not attending to His Majesty?
The Empress is attending to His Majesty now,
so I took the chance to come see you.
Hongshi.
It's been almost two months since I last talked to you.
Mother.
I also miss you very much.
Hongshi.
Do not overwork yourself with the books.
Looking at you right now,
you have lost a lot of weight.
Imperial Mother tells me to be studious day and night
so that I will have more favor with Father.
The Empress is not your birth mother.
Of course she doesn't care for your health.
You are the eldest son.
And the only prince living in the palace.
You will be the heir to the throne.
How can your father not favor you?
Hongshi.
My dear.
You have to take care of yourself.
Don't let your health suffer.
I am sad looking at you.
Mother,
I have asked Imperial Mother many times
but she says that I'm too busy with schoolwork
and doesn't allow me to see you.
Mother.
I even went to the Palace of Eternal Spring in secret.
But I couldn't even catch a glimpse of you at the gate.
Me as well.
Her Majesty never permits me to see you,
saying that I will disturb your studies.
She doesn't even let me send over
a single piece of clothing
or a plate of pastries.
I truly regret everything.
Mother, what do you mean?
It's all my fault.
I'm unable to look after you.
I am looking forward to the day
you ascend to the throne.
I will no longer be like this,
living in fear and worry.
I will make you proud, Mother.
I will honor you as the Empress Dowager,
- and repay you profusely.
- My good son.
Was that really what Consort Astuce said to the Third Prince?
Exactly, I heard it with my own ears.
Your Majesty has been so good to the Third Prince,
providing him comfortable living conditions and attentive guidance.
But after all, he is not your child.
It makes my heart cold with disappointment.
The Third Prince is older now.
He's different from the younger children.
Sadly, the Fourth Prince is inferior,
and the Fifth Prince is sickly.
Neither is fit for fostering.
The Third Prince might be immature,
but Consort Astuce is even more foolish.
Fortunately, the Third Prince still obeys Your Majesty.
He has been putting in more effort recently.
But with Consort Astute stirring the pot,
Your Majesty's good intentions for her are wasted.
"One shall repay another's gratitude in kind."
Consort Astuce seems oblivious of this, and unappreciative.
With a mother like her,
it won't matter what kind of effort I put forth.
The Third Prince's future will always be uncertain.
Consort Astuce covets the title of Empress Dowager.
How is she worthy?
How is she not??
She is the birth mother of the Third Prince.
When the Third Prince takes the throne,
she will be the Divine Mother Empress Dowager,
surpassing me, the Imperial Mother Empress Dowager.
You can see Consort Astuce is anxious
to teach this to the Third Prince now.
Her words come from her heart.
Why can't she teach them to him?
I thought that since I protect her,
she would be satisfied being a Consort Dowager in the future.
As it turns out, she is quite ambitious.
I have really underestimated her.
Your Majesty,
"Two tigers cannot dwell in one mountain."
She is no tiger.
She's a cat.
A sick cat.
Your Lordship.
Lanyi.
What made you come to the palace?
I’m not going into the palace, but leaving.
What’s the matter?
His Majesty has just recovered.
The Empress Dowager called off the horse training performance for Lixia Festival
and asked us to return to the Summer Palace.
His Majesty has just made a recovery.
He would get over-excited if he sees you perform.
So Her Majesty's decree is truly for His Majesty's own good.
Your Lordship, why would you tease me about it?
I'm not teasing.
It's just that you look so lovely wearing blue garments.
Your Lordship has been so busy that you haven't visited the Summer Palace lately.
I'll definitely go see you when I'm free.
Don't forget, Your Lordship.
Certainly.
Let’s go.
I've read memoranda for half a day.
It's so tiring.
Your Majesty has been occupied with state affairs when you have just recovered.
Your health takes priority.
I should go somewhere to unwind.
How about visiting Her Highness Concubine Vertu?
When you were sick,
Concubine Vertu served the most diligently.
Concubine Vertu is careful and attentive,
but why does it tire me when I see her?
That's because the ladies Your Majesty previously encountered
are all beautiful and talented.
Their words and smiles are pleasing.
Your eyes are viciously sharp.
You saw the core of the matter.
Take Concubine An,
she can barely read.
But her singing brings peace to the mind.
Concubine Délice is also gentle and attentive,
but I always feel like there's something lacking.
The balance between the two is definitely Concubine Sourire.
Let's not speak of her.
How about visiting Concubine An?
Or Concubine Délice?
Forget it.
I will go to the Summer Palace for a walk.
Yes.
“The Loom Stretched Seven Times.”
“The weaver hesitates over the mandarin ducks she completed.”
“Fearing someone’s fleet scissors may cut them apart.”
“Two places they fly to; one bitter separation.”
“By what means could they ever meet again?”
Why do you write such a sad verse?
I haven't seen you for thirty-seven days.
I was afraid in my heart.
No matter how afraid you are,
don't speak of such sad things.
I've been watching the stars sink and moon fall,
thinking about you all night, every night.
Unfortunately,
you can't keep coming to me like this.
Su Peisheng,
Why, in your view, do the women in the palace
look boring after seeing them too much?
They all look the same to me now.
Nothing new or special.
Your Majesty, it's beyond my knowledge.
Why not run another Concubine Selection?
How would that help?
All of them would chant "Long live the Emperor,"
and then fall as silent as trembling cicadas.
Besides having different faces, everything else is the same.
It's all different in my eyes, Your Majesty.
Each is prettier than the last.
My eyes are dazzled by their beauty.
You are getting more pleasant to talk to.
Where is this?
Your Majesty, this is the Hundred Stallion Pavillion.
It is used for taming foreign tribute horses.
Let's go take a look.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Your Majesty...
Mr. Duan.
Mr. Su.
Who is that lady riding the horse?
Her?
She is Ye Lanyi, the horse trainer in the Hundred-Stallion Pavillion.
A horse trainer.
She's in good fortune.
Have you seen something,
or heard something?
You have been unhappy
since you came back from the palace.
Huan'er, when I was attending to His Majesty,
he called your name in his dream.
I attended to His Majesty for thirty-seven days.
Although I only heard His Majesty
vaguely call your name once in his sleep,
I'm still afraid.
Huan'er,
I'm afraid of losing you one day.
The name His Majesty often calls out in the dream,
is Empress Première, Surissé, isn't it?
Yes.
While he was recuperating,
His Majesty often looked through
the relics of Empress Première alone.
When he is awake, the one he misses is Empress Première.
The reason why my name was called in his sleep
is that I look quite similar to Empress Première.
He was missing Empress Première
and happened to think of me:
an unruly shadow of Empress Première.
Besides,
I was expelled from the palace.
How could I go back again?
Huan'er,
I was surprised to find myself so timid,
and so afraid of something unexpected happening again.
It won't.
Never.
Dinner is ready.
My Lady and Your Lordship should head back together.
Let's go.
Jade loves to wear jade-colored clothes.
And with that red azalea flower,
so pretty.
I thank Your Lordship.
It's getting late. Let's all head back.
Help.
- Help.
- Huan'er,
What is that sound?
Over there.
Help!
Help! Help me! Help!
Help me...
H- Help... me...
Huan'er, don't come over here.
This person was bitten by a poisonous snake.
What should we do then?
We must save him first.
- Help!
- Here, apply this medicine onto his wound.
Jade, hold onto his legs.
Hold them down.
Where is his wound?
Only his hands are exposed. It should be on his hands.
It's right here.
- Jade, give me your handkerchief.
- Aye.
Here.
Open the container.
Pass me the medicine.
Jade, get some water. Hurry.
He's awake!
Here.
Mister, are you feeling better?
Thank you.
Thank you all for saving me.
It's only because you Dzungars
have such strong and healthy bodies.
If it was any other person, they would have lost their life already.
How can you tell I am Dzungar?
There are no flaws in your outfit,
but you mumbled in your native
language when unconscious.
When Huan'er was applying medicine,
she pointed out to me the unusual markings on your hand.
The tough calluses on your hands,
they are from years of mounted archery.
The Dzungar people won their territories on horseback,
and only those activities will leave such marks behind.
What a clever lady.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember, amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.